<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discourse of the most happy victories obtayned by the French King, against the rebels and enemies of his Maiesty With a particular declaration of all that hath beene done betweene the two armies, during the monthes of September and October, and part of Nouember. 1589. Also of the taking of the subburbes of Paris by the King. Faithfully translated out of French into English, according to the coppy imprinted at Tours. By T.D.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92937</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848829</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848829</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03003)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 736:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discourse of the most happy victories obtayned by the French King, against the rebels and enemies of his Maiesty With a particular declaration of all that hath beene done betweene the two armies, during the monthes of September and October, and part of Nouember. 1589. Also of the taking of the subburbes of Paris by the King. Faithfully translated out of French into English, according to the coppy imprinted at Tours. By T.D.</title>
                  <author>Wealsh, Luke.</author>
                  <author>T. D., fl. 1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Wolfe, and E. White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication and verses signed: Luke Wealsh.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The victories of the French King.</note>
                  <note>First leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13945:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13945:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True Diſcourſe <hi>of the moſt happy victories obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> by the French King, againſt the Rebels and enemies of his Maieſty. <hi>With a particuler declaration of all that hath béene done betweene the two Armies, during the monthes of September and October, and part of Nouember. 1589.</hi> Alſo of the taking of the Subburbes of Paris by the King.</p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated out of French into Engliſh, according to the Coppy imprinted at Tours. By T. D.</p>
            <p>LONDON: <hi>Printed by I. Wolfe, and E. White.</hi> 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13945:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13945:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable Lord Robert Deuorax, Earle of Eſſex and Ewe, Vicount of Harryford, and Bourchier, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Burchier and Louaine, maiſter of the Queenes maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Horſe, and Knight of the moſt honourable order of the Garter: Luke Wealſh wiſheth all heauenly happineſſe, and increaſe of honourable vertue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He viewe of Scipio his valiant exploites (right Honourable) was no leſſe admired amongſt the hardie Carthageni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, then the report of his conqueſtes were ioyfull among the Senators and Citizens of flouriſhing Rome. But if they in regarde of Heathen honour, and onely forworldly cauſes conceaued ſuch felicity in their victories, yeelding their graue ears to the diſcourſe therof, then need I not feare to preſent to your honors hands, the vndoubted truth of theſe happy victories obtained by the moſt noble and Chriſtian French King, who for the recouery of his right &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of Gods glory, is inforced to maintaine wars againſt them. Wherfore
<pb facs="tcp:13945:3"/> in reſpect of your honourable and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimious minde, your wiſedom and vertuous inclination, your hardineſſe in warres, and hatred to rebellion ſondrie times manifeſted to your eternall and well deſerued praiſe, as alſo to declare my well affected hart to your honour, I haue choſen you the Patrone of this warlike diſcourſe, that the noble ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits herein mentioned may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter regarded, and the more eſteemed by the name of ſo honourable a perſonage, whoſe loue as it is generally planted in the harts of all the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons of this land, ſo it is euery day augmented through hope of your neuer dying fame. Thus ſhielding my ſelfe vnder your honours protection, with hope of your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable fauour and pardon for my bolde attempt, in moſt humble manner I take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble at command Luke VVealſh.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13945:3"/>
            <head>Certain verſes written by maſter Wealſh as a thankeſgiuing vnto God, for the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſe of the King.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OVr mighty God in higheſt heauens doth ſitte,</l>
               <l>And yet behouldes all things on earth below:</l>
               <l>How godles men applies their chiefeſt witte,</l>
               <l>With might and maine his truth to ouerthrow.</l>
               <l>But praiſed be our God of greateſt power,</l>
               <l>Who can confound their doings in an howre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though all the Princes of the earth conſpire,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Lord and Chriſt his onely ſonne:</l>
               <l>They ſhalbe ſcattered in his furious ire,</l>
               <l>And be conſtraind to leaue where they begunne.</l>
               <l>For praiſed be our God of greateſt power,</l>
               <l>Who can confound their doings in an howre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By him alone all royall Kings do raigne,</l>
               <l>By him they rule and ſitte in Princely throne:</l>
               <l>Then flie you Rebels with your trayterous traine,</l>
               <l>Your ſinne and ſhame throughout the world is knowne,</l>
               <l>And prayſed be our God of greateſt power,</l>
               <l>Who did confound their doings in an howre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Pharaos ſight the ſtout Egyptian King,</l>
               <l>The Lord by Moyſes many wonders wrought:</l>
               <l>His choſen flocke from bondage great to bring,</l>
               <l>But all his threats hee leaudly ſet at nought.</l>
               <l>Yet praiſed be our God of greateſt power,</l>
               <l>Who did deſtroy his army in an howre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13945:4"/>
               <l>And thou O France whoſe fame in former daies,</l>
               <l>Did glorifie the pleaſant Weſterne partes:</l>
               <l>How oft in thee did God his wonders raiſe,</l>
               <l>Which neuer yet could mollify your hartes?</l>
               <l>But praiſed be our God of greateſt power.</l>
               <l>Who can confound his foes within an howre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What grieuous tumultes in thy townes are wrought?</l>
               <l>What rage and bloudſhed by thy City wales?</l>
               <l>What wrongfull broyles and cauſeleſſe wars are ſought?</l>
               <l>What great Rebellion on thy people falls?</l>
               <l>But prayſed be our God of greateſt power,</l>
               <l>Who can confound his foes within an howre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ieruſalem that Citty of renowne,</l>
               <l>By diuers tokens warned was of ſinne:</l>
               <l>And thou O France didſt lately ſée a Crowne</l>
               <l>Plaſt in the ſkie, by God ouer the King.</l>
               <l>As many men affirme and plainely ſhoe,</l>
               <l>A wonderous thing if that the truth be ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ceaſe your iarres obey your ſoueraigne Lord,</l>
               <l>Whom God from Heauen affirmes your louing King:</l>
               <l>Whoſe heart, whoſe hand, doth ſéeke with one accord,</l>
               <l>Your health, your wealth, and Realme in peace to bring.</l>
               <l>And bleſſed be our God of greateſt power,</l>
               <l>Who can confirme theſe bleſſings in an howre.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13945:4"/>
            <head>A true diſcourſe of the moſt happy victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries obtained by the French king, againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and enemies of his Maieſty. With a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer declaration of all that hath bene done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two Armies, during the months of September and October and part of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Alſo of the taking of the Subburbes of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris by the king.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is too common and manifeſtlye knowen with what pompe and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity the Duke <hi>de Main</hi> and all thoſe of his ſide, had vanted in euery place, of the ſuppoſed ſucceſſe which they aſſured themſelues to obtaine in the voyage which they enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in September laſt paſt, againſt royall Maieſty in the partes of <hi>Normandy.</hi> But it is more manifeſtly knowen how thoſe vainglorious brags giuen out both by wordes and writing were gain-ſaide by God in the effectes which followed, for it pleaſed him clean contrary to their Imaginations, and publiſhed boaſtinges, to turne their glory into ſhame. As by the following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe moſt plainely ſhall appeare to the comfort of all ſuch as wiſhe the aduancemente of the glorious Goſpell of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>His Maieſty hearing that the enemy approched very faſt intamped himſelfe at <hi>Arques,</hi> a good league from the towne of <hi>Dieppe</hi> by the prudent counſaile of the Lorde Marſhall <hi>de Birron.</hi> And viewing the place, hee by and by iudged, what the enemy was able to doe againſt him: whereuppon he cauſed certaine trenches to be made on the toppe of the hill, in moſt ſubſtantiall manner as farre from
<pb facs="tcp:13945:5"/> 
               <hi>Arques</hi> as a cannon can ſhoote. A deuiſe ſo excellente and pollitickely framed, that all the Army (for a néede) mighte be couered therewith, out of all danger, vppon which tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, his Maieſty planted foure péeces of great Artillerye, this being done in ſight of a faire plaine, where he ſuppoſed the enemy would come to fight, whether alſo wée might come without any daunger, this Campe of the Kings was pitched cloſe almoſt after the faſhion of the <hi>Romanes</hi> in olde time. All the companies were quartered in villages rounde about according as his Maieſty had ordained their lodginges. The meane while the enemy approched more and more very faſt, and on Friday the fiftéenth of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of September, he came and lodged his vantgard with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a league and a halfe of the towne of <hi>Diepe,</hi> whether his Maieſty was gone that morning to mark the enemies intent, who ſaw plainly by their preſent dealing, that they minded vtterly to ſpoil the ſuburbe called <hi>le Paullet,</hi> before hee came to <hi>Arques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The king therefore with all diligence fortified the ſaide ſuburbe, but eſpecially the milles which ſtoode muſt open to the enemy. Which being done, his ſaid Maieſty woulde once againe as neere as he could with ſmal company mark and ſée, how the enemy was lodged, and perceiuing through the occaſion of ſome one that they were to forwarde, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded fiue or ſixe of his company to geue them a charge, which was done to the loſſe of ſeauen of the enemy vppon that place, his Maieſty retourning at night lay in his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Arques,</hi> doing nothing al that night. But many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore day marched out of the ſubburbs of <hi>Diepe</hi> to the field who made againſt the enemy moſte hot ſkirmiges, where <hi>mounſier de Chaſtilion</hi> commanded ouer the footemen, who ſhewed himſelfe more and more a moſt ſkilfull and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant leader, in ſo much that our Arquebuzers neuer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged bullet in vaine. The horſemen alſo were ſo ſette and placed by the king, who behaued themſelues ſo well, that no perſon could paſſe to the enemy, without his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb facs="tcp:13945:5"/> commandement, otherwiſe there had béene greate diſorder among vs, ſo earneſt were our ſouldiers to the fight.</p>
            <p>Among other his Maieſty permitted certaine Engliſhe Lords well mounted and armed, and moſt ſumptuouſly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, I knew among the reſt the noble gentleman maiſter <hi>d'Euerax,</hi> brother to the right honorable Earle of Eſſex, who was one of the formoſt and forwardeſt in the fight.</p>
            <p>Who imployed themſelues ſo valiauntly and with ſuche hardy courage that they fiue many of the enemies, and in leſſe then the turning of an hand, threw them to the ground and tooke priſoners all that incountred them. About ten of the clocke this forenoone, we ſaw aboue the milles, how the enemy in great troupes came downe the hill, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their paſſage after ſome of their company which had already paſſed the brooke which ſeperated their armye and ours, and being entred in the medowe, they purpoſed to aſſault a village called <hi>Boutielle,</hi> where the kinges white cornet was, At what time wee ſawe comming againſte them the very ſame inſtant ſixe gentlemen, well armed whom we knew not, but the King was ſince certifyed, two of them wer the Lords of <hi>Saint Marke</hi> and <hi>Sturbe,</hi> which tooke their ſwordes in hand to ſuch purpoſe, with two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebuzeirs on foot, that the enemies being in number thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or thirty fiue, which before had paſſed the brooke, were conſtrained to turne their backs and wade againe through the ſame brooke, to eſcape their hard purſute, flyinge with great feare and ſorrowfull countenance. Vppon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident it is greatly to be conſidered, that if the enemy might haue had their wiles without expulſe, and that their whole Army might haue got ouer the water as thoſe few did, our litle hoaſt had béene ſoone ſeperated in the halfe, by theire mighty and huge Armye, which woulde haue béene verye hardly ioyned together againe.</p>
            <p>His Maieſty had ſent the two companies of light horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Mounſier de Lorges</hi> and <hi>Harambres</hi> to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe.
<pb facs="tcp:13945:6"/> Notwithſtanding they had by and by a contrarye commandement to goe to <hi>Arques</hi> to méete <hi>Mounſieur de Birron:</hi> but all the while there continued this day greate ſkirmiges at the milles of <hi>Paullet.</hi> And his Maieſty ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uainicing himſelfe alwayes to ſée theyr doinges, a Harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buze ſhot came and ſtrooke in the thigh of his horſe, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more bullets paſſed on the contrary ſide of <hi>Arques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now thoſe two companies of light horſmen, (of which one part belonged to my Lord the Prince of Countie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by <hi>Mounſieur d'Armillie</hi> his lieftenant) whom the king had before ſent to <hi>Monſieur de Birron,</hi> had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the ſaid <hi>Monſieur,</hi> to go and ſpie out the lodging of the enemy, who lay in a village called <hi>Martinglize</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the riuer, where alſo was the Duke, and <hi>Cheualliers d'Amall,</hi> of <hi>Nemoures</hi> and <hi>Sagonne,</hi> but our men being come to the place, ran vpon the enemy ſo fiercely, that they had no leiſure to cary word to <hi>Monſieur de Birron</hi> of that they had ſene, and with ſo great fury they did it being eager in fight, that they broke downe on horſebacke all theire rampiers or barrycades, and ſlue of the enemy more then an hundreth and fifty, ſome helde the Marques <hi>De mene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laye</hi> to be in the number, beſides diuers Captains and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good priſoners which they tooke.</p>
            <p>The Cheualliers <hi>d'Aumall</hi> and <hi>Sagonne</hi> were the firſt that fled, with four regimens of footemen, who found more ſafety in their féete, then in their ſwords. His maieſtye which was on the ſide of <hi>Diepe,</hi> perceiuing by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies doings that they determined ſome ſecrete miſchiefe, came into his quartor, where he found how thoſe of his ſide had moſt faithfully ſerued in that incounter latelye made, which was done ſo manfully, that if he had had thoſe three ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred horſes redy which afterward came, we had brought away their chiefeſt forces. Notwithſtanding we were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſorowfull for <hi>mounſieur d'Armille,</hi> who had receiued a dangerous wound through the body by a ſworde, but wee haue good hope of his recouery. On Sunday the ſeuenteeth
<pb facs="tcp:13945:6"/> of that moneth, his Maieſty cauſed a Cannon to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged againſt the enemy, on the ſide of <hi>Arques,</hi> while <hi>mounſieur de Chatellon</hi> made a moſte valiaunt ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mige, winning many priſoners that day, from the enemy, without the loſſe of any one man, and but fewe of his ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours wounded. Which was done while thoſe of our ſide recouered a village where they flew thirtie men at the leaſt. Euery day of that wéeke they ſpent in the like ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, by the meanes wherof an infinite number of gentle men and ſouldiours came of their voluntarie goodwil, and yéelded themſelues and ſeruice to the King, parte whereof were the troupes &amp; regiment of <hi>Mounſier de Rubempree</hi> which before was taken of the enimie at <hi>Gornay,</hi> who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enimies armie for the ſafegard of their armes. On Teweſday the one &amp; twentieth by breake of day, about fiue of the clocke in the morning, the enimie marched out from the ſaide Martinglize in battel ray, ſo wel ordered as might be, their faces ſet againſt <hi>Arques</hi> and againſt the ſide of our <hi>Swizers,</hi> the moſt part of their horſemen in ſundrie troupes wonderfull ſtrong and thicke, their footemen in their winges excellently well placed. Then the Lord <hi>de Billin</hi> with two thouſand ſhot, was choſen to giue the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet vpon vs. But his maieſtie who was a horſebacke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till midnight, perceiuing that the einimies intent was to winne the riuer, and to paſſe the ſame, for which purpoſe they had made certaine bridges of wood to be caſt ouer, he preſently ſet ſuch order in euery place, that they coulde doe him no hurt without great loſſe to themſelues. And now hauing ſéene the order of their battell incontinent hee ſent forth his light horſemen: And the company belonging to my Lord, the Prince (gouerned by <hi>Mounſieur de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tater</hi>) and his maieſties owne Cornet, wherein were my Lords <hi>le graund prior, le graunde Eſquier, le count Rochfoucaue, le count de Rouſye, le count de Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> with diuers other gentlemen which were neareſt to the perſon of his maieſtie. And theſe he placed by thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:13945:7"/> were his footemen, deuiding his <hi>Swizers</hi> in two partes. And in this order he ſet againſt the enimie, knowing that God could as well vanquiſh with a ſmall as a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, hauing earneſtly deſired his aide, as well by his publike as priuate prayers. Then marched he againſt his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with ſuch reſolued and princely courage, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter and charges which hee gaue againſt his enimies (being in number twentie fiue thouſand men of warre, and himſelfe but nine thouſand) was moſt wonderfull. The enimie loſt at that time nere hand fiue hundreth men, beſide priſoners and wounded ſouldiours: And the reſt were in ſuch feare, that eightie of our men chaſed and put to flight a thouſand horſemen of the enimies, following the purſute moſt couragiouſly, and crying, <hi>God ſaue the King.</hi> But they were ſo aſtoniſhed, that the helpe which the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> had prouided to ſend to ſuccour them, ſtanding in a raye behinde, were ſo diſordered by their owne men whom wée had in chaſe, who mingled them ſelues among the reſt for ſafegarde, that they were all brought into ſuch an horrible confuſion, that had his Maieſtie receiued the forces which afterwarde came, it had ſurely béene the end of our miſeries, for we had not left one of them liuing. But our liues are not yet ſufficiently amended, that we ſhoulde receiue ſo great a bleſſing of God. But when his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties forces were refreſhed, the launce-knights of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, to the number of fiftéene hundred preſented themſelues in a little trench that was neareſt to the enimy (which was kept by part of our two hundred launce-knights) who lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp their hands, proteſted vnto them, and deſired to yéelde them ſelues to the King, condicionally that euerye one of vs might put vp our weapons. This was eſtéemed ſuch good newes among vs, and ſo credibly belieued, that we made no other account but to receiue them with great ioy, and thereupon we were commanded that wee ſhoulde put vp euery man his weapon: ſo we mingled our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them without any ſuſpicion of treaſon, ſhaking one
<pb facs="tcp:13945:7"/> another by the hand, then two of the Captaines of the ſaide launce-knights went to méete with the King: but being examined ſodenly, faultring in their wordes, and ſcant knowing what they ſaide, named themſelues ſeruants to the Duke <hi>de Maine.</hi> The meane while they fedde vs with faire wordes, onely to delay the time till their whole troupes of horſemen might come to ſuſtaine them, deſiring much to ſée the King. But to come to the effect of their treaſon, the King hauing no confidence in them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs to march downe the medowes from them. And the while theſe villaines paſſed toward the Switzers; as though in déed they would yéelde themſelues wholy to the King. But on a ſodaine they ſeaſed vpon <hi>Mounſieur le countie de Rochford:</hi> and ſéeing no more our horſemen before them (and contrariwiſe theirs approching ſtill) they began to ſet vpon vs with all their might, while fiftéene hundreth more of their horſemen came marching along the Medowes in battell raye, very ſtrong and cloſe to chaſe vs. We being no more but two hundred and fiftie, or thrée hundred horſemen at the moſt. The Cornet of <hi>Mounſieur de Monpancier,</hi> and the Cornet of the great Eſquier go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before vs.</p>
            <p>This notable and ſubtill treaſon aſtoniſhed vs ſo much, that the moſt part of our company maugre our chiefeſt commanders, went backe towarde our Switzers, which Switzers neuer moued or ſhronke for all that, but ſtood ſtill moſt firmely, ſhewing ſuch a manly countenance, that the enimie ſuſpected our ſhrinking was but for a pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to bring them within the daunger of the Switzers, as was a great likelyhood: for retyring in ſuch good order as we did, wee put our ſelues in two partes: our Arquebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers very well placed, ſo that if the enimie had paſſed a little farther (which he durſt not doe) they had ſurely had their payment,, and the whiles our Cannons played vpon them and killed many. And they ſéeing, that by the diligence of the King, we which were before in great diſorder, were ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13945:8"/> ſoone ſet in faire and good order, who in this extremitie being on the other ſide, to gather the troupes together, to the end he might expulſe theſe traiterous launce-knights (which he did) he ſhewed himſelfe both King, Captaine, and ſouldier, al at one time, bearing himſelf with ſuch a princely courage that thereby he became the onely myrror to incourage the Switzers them ſelues, as they haue ſince confeſſed. But his magnanimious and hardie exploites was not done without perrill of his royall perſon, for one of his bootes was pearced, and his horſe was hurt with a Caliuer ſhotte at what time his Maieſtie fought both on horſbacke and on foot, with the aſſured aſſiſtance of the Marſhall <hi>de Birron,</hi> and ſo much preuailed, as though the enimie had had the leſſer, and his Maieſtie the greater number.</p>
            <p>The enimie then retired himſelfe very ſhamefully, and ſore ſcattered, leauing their dead &amp; ours, in the fielde behinde them, ſéeking to ſhroude themſelues in the village of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinglize, marching about by the hill to ſcape from vs. On the ſide of Dipe to <hi>paullet, Mounſieur de Chaſtelon,</hi> and <hi>Mounſieur de Guittery</hi> had a good number of footmen, of the which <hi>mounſieur de Chaſtillon</hi> brought fiue hundred good Calléeuers, who came very fitly, the very inſtant that the treaſon was diſcouered. His Maieſtie ſtayed yet in the fielde and commaunded that certaine péeces of Ordenance ſhould be brought to our little trenches, to bee diſcharged againſt Martinglize wher the enimie laye. Which being done, he after commanded all perſons in moſt ſolemne ſorte to render thankes vnto God for their deliuerance, euen as he had before deſired his aide in his iuſt cauſe. Then great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did his Maieſtie commend the ſeruice of the Switzers in the preſence of their Captaines, and in drinking, he drunke vnto them for the valiant exploites performed that day by them.</p>
            <p>And to the end you may know all thinges that hath paſſed, that nothing may be forgotten here worthy the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, we are moſt credibly informed that <hi>Saga collonel</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:13945:8"/> the light horſemen on the enimies ſide dyed that day, who was ſince buried in Roan with <hi>mounſienr Saint Vidal</hi> chiefe maiſter of their Artillery, the Lord of <hi>Saint Andrew</hi> brother to the Countie of <hi>Saux, mounſieur de Vuiuille</hi> yonger ſonne to the Marſhall of Vienele, the Chiuallier de <hi>Picart</hi> and many other of name and account whom I can not remember, we tooke priſoners y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Earle of Billin, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of the Campe. Tremblecourt, <hi>le count de Loraine</hi> who had the firſt regiment, and <hi>mounſieur Sauelack</hi> with diuers other Captaines for the fight was ſo heat that nothing could be heard, which was the cauſe that manie died which woulde gladly haue yéelded themſelues to our mercie. And although we deſerued no ſuch fauour at Gods handes, yet he bleſſed vs in ſuch ſort that we loſt but ſeauen and twentie men in all this fight: neuertheleſſe we were verie ſorrowfull for the death of <hi>Mounſieur the Count de Rouſy</hi> (brother to the Count <hi>de la Rouchfoucaue</hi>) and <hi>Mounſieur de Bacqueuille</hi> whoſe vertues were moſt commendable among all men but eſpecially the valiant and hardy ſeruice which they performed in this fight, wherein they declared their wonderfull courage. Neither can I forget <hi>Mounſieur le graund Prior</hi> who ſéeing <hi>Monſieur Sagonne,</hi> (a moſt proud and ambitious enemie, and one that boaſted himſelfe ouer all men, for the opinion hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued in his manhood and ſtrength of armes) he called him to the fight, and ſo néere they ioyned togither that when they parted, <hi>Sagonne</hi> bore away his markes: And ſée the iudgement of God vpon this vnhappie man, lighting down from his horſe he broke his necke.</p>
            <p>The next day after, that is to ſay, on Saterday the thrée and twentie my Lord Stafford (Ambaſſadour to the moſt Noble Quéene of Englande) arriued at Déepe, bringing both money and victuals, but he ſawe not his Maieſtie till the next day. About midnight the ſame Saterday wee perceaued that the enemie changed his opinion, and that he would rayſe his armie (which in déede he did on the Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day
<pb facs="tcp:13945:9"/> morning very early without any ſound of Driumne or Trumpet in ſight of his Maieſtie and all his armie) which were for the moſt part in battell raye on the otherſide of the hill, where my Lord Ambaſſadour mette him: this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moouing of theirs was doone with ſuch great feare and ſo cowardly, that they left their wounded men in their villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges behinde them, leauing by the way both their victualles and munition for warre, and to their greater ſhame, they ſtaied not ſo much as to giue their Sentriles warning to retire or ſaue themſelues. They tooke their iourney as though they went to a Towne called <hi>Ewe,</hi> but we purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them tooke ſome priſoners, who being demaunded the cauſe of their ſoddaine retire, were founde in diuers tales concerning the ſame, for ſome ſayde it was becauſe of the comming of the Engliſh ſhippes which lately ariued there, wherein they doubted great aide to be ſent to his Maieſtie. Some other ſaide it was vppon occaſion of placing of newe Gouernours among them, in ſtéede of thoſe which had béen ſlaine, whereupon great ſtrife grew among them, ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of one man, ſome chooſing an other: but we muſt referre that vnto God, who can worke confuſion among his enemies when it pleaſeth him. Then the enemie went paſt the forreſt and riuer, to <hi>S. Vax, Quinqueuille,</hi> and <hi>Bures,</hi> &amp; lodged himſelfe on the otherſide of the towne of Déepe, where he ſpredde his troopes all about, intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe in the néereſt Villages, as Ianuall, Boutiles, Apeuiell, and others. The king ſéeing that cauſed his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell to be pitched in the plaine néere <hi>Arques,</hi> and ſent the regiment of <hi>Monſieur de la Gard</hi> into the Caſtle of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> (but the day before he brought all his armie into Déep and the ſuburbes of the ſame, with thrée péeces of great or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance) and being come, all that night he cauſed great and large trenches to be made in a place called the Mount of Cattes, on the ſide of the enemie, ſo that he had a faire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in the morning, in which place he lodged a part of his footmen, vnder the Gouernement of <hi>Monſieur de Chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13945:9"/> with thirtéene enſignes of Suitzers: the reſt of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie he placed in the towne, and in the fort of Paulet, but in the fort of the Mount of Cats on the ſide of <hi>Ianuell</hi> the King cauſed two double Cannons to bee planted, which were ſhott off vpon the enemie without any ſhott in vaine, becauſe they were all on an heape, and their horſemen could not come into their quarter, but by the fauour of the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</p>
            <p>The firſt day of October the enemie planted ſixe péeces of ordenance vpon the toppe of the hill by <hi>Ianuall</hi> ſhootting fiue or ſixe vollies of ſhot into the towne, wherewith was ſlaine one of the Kings Cookes, a woman, a maiden, and a boye, doing alſo great hurt vnto two ſhippes which lay at Anker in the hauen. But they withdrewe ſoone after their Cannons from that place, becauſe by our Cannons their maſter gonner was ſlaine, &amp; two péeces of their ordenance diſmounted, which was done by a ſkilfull Engliſh Canno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neir, who was preſented to the King by my Lord Stafford, Ambaſſadour to the Quéene of England. The fourth day of October the enemie broke downe all their Rampiers or Gabions, becauſe our men viſited them more then they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, making them to forſake them euery foote, And ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they could no better preuaile the enemie retired himſelf againe with great ſhame and loſſe of men, and the vtter ruine of his armie (after he had vſed all the cruelties that might be) taking his way toward Picardie, not daring to fight againſt the helpe which was comming towarde the King. His Maieſtie little thinking of the enemies ſodaine departure, ſawe how he raiſed his campe on a ſoddaine in ſight of them all, whereupon he preſently imagined that he went to fight againſt the helpes which were comming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde his Maieſtie, (which were brought by the Earle of <hi>Soyſſon,</hi> the Duke <hi>de Longeuiell,</hi> and the Marſhall <hi>d'Aumont</hi> before they could ioyne with his Maieſtie. And the more his highneſſe miſtruſted the matter by their ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into thrée ſeuerall places and neuer farre off from his
<pb facs="tcp:13945:10"/> Maieſties armie. But his grace knowing that theſe helpes were come within ſeauen or eight leagues, he determined with thrée or foure hundred horſemen to go méete and ioine with them, leauing the Marſhall <hi>de Birron</hi> in Déepe with all the reſt of the armie. And although the enemie was but fiue leagues off when his Maieſtie ioyned with his newe forces, yet in ſight of them all: his highneſſe tooke parforce the towne and Caſtle of <hi>Gamaſche,</hi> and ſince hee tooke in like manner the towne of <hi>Ewe,</hi> which was as great an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion as might be to procure the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> to the fight. But in ſtéede thereof, and fearing he ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained therevnto, he moſt cowardly went ouer the riuer of Some, into Picardie, ſéeking to excuſe this ſhamefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire with a greater diſgrace, for he publiſhed abroad that he was conſtrained to come downe into Picardie to take him ſelfe poſſeſſion of the townes of that Prouince, which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was before intreated of by his Deputies, in the towne of <hi>Aras</hi> at what time the ſaide Duke <hi>de maine</hi> had bound himſelfe to the Spaniardes to deliuer all thoſe townes into their hands: but the Spaniards wold not come to aide him, before he had performed what he was bound to doo, vnto which compoſition hee was in doubt the people of thoſe townes would not eaſily cenſent. The King which had a ſpeciall deſire to bring the enemie to an open battell: ſéeing he would not do it ſo long as he was on this ſide of the riuer of <hi>Some,</hi> and now being the firſt that had paſſed the ſayde riuer, he thought it now vnpoſſible hee ſhould be brought thereunto. His Maieſtie therefore reſolued himſelfe to ſtay for the enemies returne backe againe, not caring much for his paſſing into Picardie, for that he knew the people wold neuer yéelde vnto him. And although the Frenchmen in their heate and naturall haſtineſſe, ſell ſometime into ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and rebellion, yet he knew their anger laſted not long, and that they are not ſo farre degenerated from the opinion of their Anceſtors, that they would (to pleaſe another mans minde) ſubiect themſelues to a ſtrange Gouernement, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:13945:10"/> ſo many examples before their eyes to beware, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo that there is no Dominion in the worlde more ſwéete vnto them, then their owne Countrie.</p>
            <p>So his Maieſtie ſtaying yet a while in the town' of Déep, as well for the affaires of Normandie (where he lefte the Duke <hi>de Monponcier</hi>) as alſo to receiue the foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Engliſhmen, ſent vnto him by the moſt renowmed Quéene of England. He departed from the ſaid Déepe the one and twentieth of October, taking ſmall iourneyes on this ſide the riuer, kéeping himſelfe ſtill on the enemies ſide vntill he came to <hi>Meulan,</hi> ten leagues from <hi>Paris,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the king with all ſpéed purpoſed to goe, thinking that the enemie for his credits ſake, and in reſpect of the promiſe which he made to al thoſe of his ſide, hereafter to performe, would come to their aide at the leaſt, and what he woulde not doe to winne Déepe, he would doe without faile for the defence of <hi>Paris.</hi> In conſideration wherof the king thought good to go ouer the riuer of <hi>Seinne</hi> at the bridge of <hi>Mullin,</hi> which done he came preſently to <hi>Paris,</hi> for two cauſes: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to compell the enemie to the fight, or to make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire from <hi>Picardie,</hi> where by treaſon he ſodeinly tooke the towne of Ferre, and he might well doe the like by others, eſpecially becauſe the moſt part of the nobilitie of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie came to méet the king. His Maieſtie a mile from Paris lodged his armie in the néereſt vilages round about, and the verie ſame daie his Grace went all about to ſuruaie the trenches along the ſuburbes on the other ſide of the riuer. And ſodeinly by the aduice of the Princes and Marſhals of France, with other expert Captaines, his Maieſtie deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to aſſault the ſayde ſuburbes the next morning by breake of daie, by thrée ſeuerall troupes, and in thrée ſundrie places, whom, he diuided himſelfe into this ſorte. In one of the troups were the foure thouſand Engliſhmen, vnder the gouernment of my Lord <hi>Willoughbie</hi> their generall, with two regiments of French men, and one regiment of Swi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, with the Marſhall de Birron accompanied by the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron
<pb facs="tcp:13945:11"/> de Birron his ſonne, and <hi>Monſieur de Gettrie,</hi> with diuerſe other noble men, who had commandement to aſſalt the ſuburbes of Saint Marcel and Saint Vidor. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond troupe was of foure regiments of French men, two regiments of Swiſers, and foure companies of aduenturers with the Marſhall of <hi>Aumont</hi> accompanied with <hi>Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur le Grand</hi> Eſquier, and <hi>Monſieur de Rieulx</hi> Marſhall of the field, and a good number of Nobles and Gentlemen, who had in charge to aſſault the ſuburbes of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> and Saint Michael. The third troupe with ten regimentes of French ſouldiers, one regiment of Lanceknights, condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>Monſieur de la Noe</hi> &amp; <hi>Monſieur de Chaſtellon</hi> aſſaulted the ſuburbs of Saint Germain Bucie, and <hi>Nele,</hi> each troupe hauing a good number of Gentlemen on foote well armed, to ſuſtaine the footemen, if anie extreame reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhould be made. Moreouer, on the rereward of euery troupe, two Canons and two culuerings were planted. He alſo had ſeparated all the horſmen of the armie in thrée com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, his Maieſtie commanding ouer the firſt, <hi>Monſieur le Count de Soyſon</hi> ouer the ſecond, and the Duke of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueuill ouer the third, each of them appointed ouer one of the thrée ſides of the ſuburbes. And in this order the firſt of Nouember by breake of the daie, the ſaid ſuburbes were ſo ſhaken by the Kings power, that in leſſe then an houre they were all taken, with the loſſe of fiftéene hundreth of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie or there about, winning alſo the ſame time fouretéene Enſignes and thirtéene péeces of ordinance great and ſmall. And with ſuch furie we followed the chaſe of our enemies y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our men were mingled among them, euen within the verie gates of the citie. And had the Kings great ordinance come ſo ſoone as it was appointed, the gates of <hi>Paris</hi> had bin ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beaten downe before they could anie waie haue ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened them. So his Maieſtie came into the ſuburbes of S. <hi>Iames</hi> about ſeauen or eight of the clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the people crying along the ſtréetes with a loud voice, <hi>God ſaue the King,</hi> with more ſhew of ioy, then any feare
<pb facs="tcp:13945:11"/> at all. Beſide, the King obſerued ſo good an order among his ſouldiers, that no man ſtarted from his companie for anie pillage, till the quarters were appointed what they ſhoulde doe. The enimie about an hundred and fiftie ſhot, tooke for their defence the Abbie of Saint <hi>Germaine,</hi> ſhewing them ſelues as though they would holde it perforce, as they might verie well doe by reaſon of the ſtrength thereof. But about midnight being by vs charged to render the ſame, they gaue ouer their holde, and then was his Maieſtie maiſter of all the ſuburbes beyond the water, which are eſtéemed almoſt as bigge as the Citie of London within the wals. All that daie we imployed about the intrenching of our ſelues before the gates of the Citie, and in ſetting Warders in euerie place. His Maiſtie was aduertiſed about midnight, that the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> came into the Citie of Paris with his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Whereby the King had part of his wiſh, becauſe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie was now retired from Picardie. He would therefore trie if he woulde fulfill the other part of his deſire, that is to make battaile againſt him, that he might not altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute his iuſtice againſt the wals of the Citie, and his owne ſubiects who were greatly ſeduced by the bad perſuaſions of his enemies, wherevpon he ſtayd all the Thurſdaie to ſée if they would come forth to the fight. But ſéeing they ſhewed not anie féeling of their loſſe receiued the daie before, the king came forth of the ſuburbes the Friday morning, and ſet himſelfe in battaile raie offering fight to the enimie, but ſtaying in the field from eight of the clocke in the morning, vntill eleuen, and ſéeing all that time no man appearing, hée marched quite from thence, contenting himſelfe for that time, to haue enterpriſed and executed vpon that Citie, that which heretofore was neuer done, leauing his enemies a perpetuall reproch among all men, that being offered the fight, durſt neuer come thereto. Which may ſerue for a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall warning hereafter, neuer more to beléeue the greate brags and baunts which they haue and ſhall publiſh of their great valour and courage, which was a manifeſt token to
<pb facs="tcp:13945:12"/> the inhabitants, how néere they were brought to their utter ruine and confuſion, and as for the helpe which they had, it was almoſt worſe vnto them then the loſſe of all their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. And I cannot thinke but they did at this time ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently learne to their coſt, that they cannot ſtand in ſafetie, without the kéeping of a great &amp; mightie armie, the charge whereof would be worſe vnto them in the end, then if they were taken by the ſurie of the enemie. And no doubt but it would be the vniuerſall deſolation of that faire and wealthie Citie, which is the chiefe and principall ornament in the Realme, of whoſe welfare and ſafetie his Maieſtie hath plainly ſhewed he hath more tender care then themſelues.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13945:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
